Welcome back, let's move to another section, which is a network devices.
What are the network devices?
These are the devices which make actually a network a network.
You are understanding my world, it actually making our all networking area, our land,
when, pan or ever, man, whatever it is, so these are the devices, which, which is
used to make these devices communicating to each other so efficiently and scalable.
So if you are, you have to system, connect into each other, a cable or a wireless, then
it is just of P2P and it is good, but if you are working on a large area, you are working
for a school, working for a college, working for a company, then you need an advertising
device, which will share your data from one end to another end efficiently and easily
scalable, okay?
Networking devices are the fundamental hardware component that enable the establishment
of connection and the efficient control of networking traffic within a component network.
These devices are meticulously designed to manage their operations with each operating
at a specific level of the OSI model, okay?
So the some models work on the layer one, some on the layer two, some on that layer
three, so this is how this device work.
In this presentation, we will delve into the most commonly used networking device exploring
their functional and significance before we dive into individual devices, let's establish
some key terminology widely used in network literature and the corporate word, okay?
No, so what are the white terms that we use in our corporate word or in a network word?
These are end devices and intermediary devices, what are end devices?
I have a system, a computer, laptop, a mobile, a tablet, these are end devices.
Now what are the intermediary devices?
It's like you have a Wi-Fi in your house, so you have mobile, you have laptop which
is connected to your Wi-Fi and there is a router, okay?
So where the ISP, internet service provider, ISP is the one that provides us internet
is connected router, then router is providing us internet.
So this router, this home router, this Wi-Fi router is a intermediary device, okay?
End devices are the critical points where data flow as the originates or terminates within
a network, either so we are using the end devices.
In a corporate, we always talk about the end devices, who is using end devices and this
is like word.
So these are the devices from where either actually the information is originated or
the from where they are getting that data, they are getting the information.
These devices can be diverse, ranging from most like computer server to client, such as
web browser email client, each end device assigned a unique address, you know, IP address,
as well as there is a micro device, you will talk about this.
Typically an IP address which serves as an as its identifier on the network, enabling
this has data routing and communication, yeah, no.
What is intermediary devices?
This devices act as a backbone of a network, connecting end devices and facilitating transmission
of data.
This category and we are going to avoid array of hardware such as hub switches, router
detectors, gateway firewall, access point.
Now what are the hubs?
What are the switches?
What are the routers?
What are the repeaters?
What are the gateway?
And what are the access buttons?
Access point?
Now, in a company, we have a switch, okay?
We have switch is connected to our access point, access point are just like our routers.
They are connecting directly to ethernet via via wired cable and now this access point
providing a Wi-Fi internet to my laptop in a wireless network to my mobile in a wireless
network, okay.
So this access point provide of us a internet through a wireless medium.
Now firewall, you know firewall, firewall is widely widely used by all companies to protect
their data, to protect their network from any malicious attack.
Either it can be an IP attack, it can be any type of attack.
So it is firewall whenever you heard of our firewall, you said also no, firewall is used
to filter out traffic, okay, generally and vanishes.
It filters out traffic, F for firewall, F for filter.
Same way gateway repeaters, router switches and hubs are used, you will talk about them
in a later section.
But primary response will involve critical function like file data forwarding, amplifying or translating
data packet to insert smooth and efficient network operation, yes, no purpose of networking
device, while we use network device, expanding coverage as we know, they peter now access
point is the one that providing us the Wi-Fi, but there is a user which is sitting at
the corner of a building and we are not he is not getting a board internet now what?
Then the repeater is used, which in here is the signal strength, okay, so there is a user
sitting in a 10 meter away and he is getting a lower signal strength from an access point.
So there we put a repeater there, it is the signal strength, which he received from access
point, it enhanced it and send it to user, network interconnection for network interconnection,
we have access points, we have access switch, we have distribution switch, okay, we will
talk about it, network safeguarding, network safeguarding through filter of connections, so
it can be done on a firewall, traffic management, yeah, router do it very well, now switch
are capable of those to routing to make a routing table a been a better way, so they can
transfer any, so they can make a connection very efficiently, data packet direction and wireless
connectivity, what are the routers, the traffic directors, router operated the network layer
of the Wi-Fi, now where the OSI in OSM model, where the network layer comes, we will talk
about this, and forwarding data packet based on their IP address, so they make a route,
so they actually made a routing table on which they have IP address, they have MAC address
everything they have, so they know which data is coming from where and from where he
went to, so the user question for internet network communication, instead data reaches its
correct destination of code diverse network, like in data, access point wireless gateway is similar
to a router, but when we focus on wireless connectivity, it features built-in antennas,
not a free access point have antennas, okay, transmitters and adaptor, correcting various
words and wireless devices, access point can be fed, yeah, to carry memory or thin,
remotely manage, yes, so we have fat, app is as well that we can configure, very time using
an ethernet cable, the access cable or thin, which we put on a roof over building,
so and we can manually configure them, just like a sisco mirror key, let's go for a mirror
key, sisco mirror key, google it and you get a lot of access point, which are configured
remotely, you don't have to go to there, so right now what we are the network is going
enhancing itself, okay, we are upgrading ourselves, we don't have to visit to user place,
we don't have to visit to open network devices, we are sitting on our table, we are operating
everything, so round three years back, it was I was first introduced with this, now at
that moment I have to just sit in my chair and from there I can watch everything, my fire
wall, my S G RAM, my access point, my switches, everything and I am the one that managing
more than 10 location of a company, okay, so I manage a more than 10 location of a company
from sitting one on a one location and in a chair, I don't have to worry about how this
since happen, I don't have to worry about to go and physically check the devices, so this
is the power of a cloud, okay, so if you using cloud or hybrid technologies in your company
or in your home, this is amazing thing, this is literally amazing thing, okay, move on, get
away into weekly hubs, bridges, segmenting, network, what is the gateway, gateway is facilitate
into work between different network technologies, such as open system, interconnection,
OSM model and Transviser control protocol, entire protocol, this is actually, so if we are
understanding a network, how it data packet moves, we use OSM model to describe or to understand
how it was actually packet is moving, but we are not using OSM model, we are actually
using, the implementation is of actually of TCP and IP model, okay, so this thing is,
you have to take in your notes, you interact and ask you that OSM model is okay, but
we are using this model, so no, they are using TCP/I model, TCP/IP model, OSM model is
just to understand or just to tell how the packet moves, so they translate, this is between
disparate protocols acting like a router with a translation capability making seamless
communication possible across where I had very network architecture, bridges, segmenting
network, bridge a connect hold on network segments along large network to be divided into
smaller power, more management units, they regulate traffic flow and can filter data packets
to hover forward in the enhancing network efficiency while once popular bridges are large
living in the place where switches due to later, so it is actually, so now we have switches
which are, which have, we can say that they have all the facilities that bridges are doing
at that moment of time, so we replace them with switches, of course we do not want two things,
if one can do both of the functionality then here, now what will we do, so there is a
you have a large area to cover just like me, at that moment of time I was actually handling
null to tell the questions and for that everyone has a separate hub, okay, so it will
be better for me to manage, okay, if everyone has different IPs, every location or different
IPs, every location is tagged in a different way, so I can easily find out that this
is the IP, so this IP belongs to this location and I can troubleshoot accordingly, okay,
so this is how device bridges is used and now it is moving with the switches only, switch
but intelligent traffic manager, okay, just remember tech switch are getting more and more
intelligent, more and more intelligent as they are connecting to cloud, previously they
are not connecting to cloud, so we have to manually put a wired, cat six, or our device in
ethernet port of our cable, okay, or we can sell a console cable, console cable is used,
it is a type of cable which looks like a cat six years, cat six years or whatever, so
you have to put it inside the switch, now one end at the switch, one end at your laptop
or computer, whatever it is, and now you have to go into that system and you use your
CLI command line interface to configure that, I think your understanding what is actually
happening, you take a simple wired cable, one end at the switch, one end your system and
now you can communicate with your switch through your laptop or a system or a desktop, okay,
and use it to configure it, you put a different IP in your system and you can put that
IP in your switch, this is how it works previously but now you can sit on a chair and easily
configure every device, now the intelligent traffic manager because it needs network efficiency,
smart data forwarding limited network information, so it just simply improves network
efficiency by intelligent C, intelligently directing data to its specific destination rather
than what cutting is to all devices like how this targeted transmit some reduce necessary
traffic and optimized communication between network components, okay, smart data forwarding
like simple devices switches gather information from incoming packet forward, only to
appropriate destination this intelligent system from there able to learn a studio the
MAC address of the connectivity which is making informed forward hazards, okay, so they may
actually make the IP, so it's actually make a table according to that, no, limited network
information orientation forwarding switches generally maintain only limited information
about other nodes on that with their primary focus is from direct efficient communication
with a large local segment rather than convincing it for what routing, no, the type of switches
we have, we have L1 L2 L3, okay, P, L1 is just like a dumb switch, dumb switch, he
don't know anything, okay, he just like a dumb switch, there is a box which if you put
Ethernet cable it will work, I will say it will not work, so I think you can't do anything,
you can't do anything, there's a native LAN of one, there's no wheel LAN, so what is
a wheel LAN, yeah, wheel LAN stands for what should locally day network, okay, so right now
you have a company, you have how's whatever it is, just resume you have a company you're
working on a company, there's a printer, okay, there's a desktop laptop, there is a camera,
there's a acceptance, okay, now you want printer on a separate wheel LAN, so what is actually
happening when we're catering a wheel LAN, so that both like weight transfer data or whatever you're
making a different wheel LAN for every particular device, we'll make a wheel LAN for a printer,
we'll make a wheel LAN different wheel LAN for a system, now there is a separate word for them,
okay, there is a separate word for them, they can't communicate to each other, okay, so
it provides security, basically it provides security, we will talk about this on a legislation,
just for a basic I'm saying that, wheel LAN is what should locally day network, you have
a LAN of a company, locally day network of a company in that local area network, you have
different what should locally day network, so there is a lot of section is there in your
system, you may be heard noise from the kids which are playing outside, I don't know why
they are playing this, okay, there's a play because they are kids, okay, just ignore if you're
getting any noise, and if not, that's good, so let's back to a little bit, just I'll do switches,
operate at the data layer, which is a laptop or same model, just keep it down, keep it down on your
daily only notes, you will understand when we talk about this OSI model, TCCI model, wheel
LAN in a feature sections, forward database on Mac address, it worked on a Mac address,
generally less expensive, definitely, because in less intelligence, less expensive, so
you also have to manage your skills, so you get paid more, okay, say this course with
your friend, so they also get paid more if you want, however no friend want that my other
friend, but there's some of them, they like that they, to be both brothers, earn and
spend together, so don't share with your friends, okay, share with your brothers from
another mother, let's move, let's move back to the road, okay, let's say a less expensive
primary connect devices within the same network segment, with a LAN, okay, so table for small
to meet up such a network or as as devices, where routing is not needed, routing as one
understand, yeah, I'll just reach, operate at the network layer, that's why it's code L3,
so L2, data link layer, L3, network layer, perform routing based on IP address, now in L2
there's an routing is not needed, then we can use here, but in switch of L3, there is
a routing because we it's working on a IP model, IP address, can route traffic between
different network segment, so here L3, we can communicate different villains to each
other, now let us zoom, we have a different file and for a computer laptop and we had
different file and for printer, now we want that our computer printer is sending some data
to print, we used control P, so it will communicate to different will have, now how this
can be visible, if you have L3 switch, so it will data go to L3 switch, from first it
go from your laptop to access point, then from access point to access switch, access switch
to distribution switch, then distribution switch, which is a L2 switch, then there is a core
switch, this is L3 switch, now here it will say, okay, so you want to go to printer
will add, because L2 switch, not able to interact with the different will add, so L3
should say, okay, you want a different printer will add, now he will send your data to printer
will add, and now you get your printer, so this is how it works, so remember MAC address,
it is working on MAC address, MAC address working on IP address, typically more expensive,
definitely, because if it providing us a functionality of communicating different will have,
it should be expensive, I therefore large more complex network repair, intivalent communication,
QS, okay, and advanced security features, so this is how L2 and L3 is working, if you have
to understand how is it is working and everything, everything just visualise in your mind,
you do not have to write much, okay, I have to mute my mobile, because it is making a lot
of noise, okay, if you are not able to understand what is QS, it is quality of service, okay,
next move, what is the NIC, what is the firewall, so NIC is network interface card, it is
the question that is asked by an interviewer, a lot of times, literally a lot of times,
because it is very important, however, with the interval asked as a professor, they can
ask you what is switches, what is access point, what is access switch, this is, but I will
do an L3 difference over not access to flexors, because it is a high level of knowledge,
okay, basically it is not access to a flexors, but NIC, firewall, they are used to ask
in an interview, network interface card is a hardware component operating at the data link
layer of the OSM model, essential for enabling a device to connect to network, okay, each
NIC feature one or more, port design to connect where is type of cable, but if you parent
a signal acting as a physical and logical interface between a computer and the network
medium, without NSC a device cannot connect over and over simple, if you have a network
interface card in your system, in your laptop, in your desktop, then you can communicate
over a network, else not, firewall, a network action, if I have a limited device existing
as a hardware or software that operate across various layers of the same model depending
on its type, now, why it is saying existing as high as either hardware or software, so
when you are in a company, okay, you are using a company internet, that is okay, it is
going through a hardware coming from a hardware, when you are in a home, where is your
firewall, tell me, where is your firewall, you are using a private internet, so at that
moment of company use their software, so which filter out, every data you send to your
system, send from your system over your private hotspot, private internet, it go through
the firewall, it come through through the software firewall, okay, so it just for your
production, just for your safety, it paramount purpose is to safeguard a network from
an unauthorized access and malicious attack by a dependency in person predefined policies
and those firewall's are critical for maintaining network security integrity, just remember
this one, firewall's are critical for maintaining network security and integrity, now what
is the function, encryption, authentication, logging, auditing, okay encryption, so we are
sending data outside our network, so we need to encrypt, as well everyone can bypass that
and use that information, so if we encrypt, no one is able to find out what is our plain
text, authentication, you are coming to your office, now he need to identify that this system
is belongs to me, okay, this user belongs to me, this is in my network, authentication, logging,
log, you are sending your traffic to, you have to do a lot of logging, because there's a lot
of people sending some information from your here, from company system to outside, now you
use logging to find out that, okay, so this system through IP, this system is sent connected
into this website and he is doing this thing, so it can be usually logging, then there is
a auditing, auditing in this, that used when there is a audit, there is a audit in there
a company, you know company, so to find out that this is the, just to, we can say it is
a type of report that tells that which user did what, there is a multiple user now on
the firewall, now you have to identify that which administrator changes which, which
thing, which policies which, uh, VPNs, you are told which IP address is changed, so this
is all about auditing, now types of powerful, we have, we have proxy firewall, we have
state full inspection firewall, we have unified threat management firewall, due to firewall,
we have third focused next generation firewall, we have next generation firewall, okay,
so, uh, just read them, you don't have to learn everything, go through a stateful inspection
firewall, monitor the state of active connection, and make decision based on the context
of the traffic, it allows traffic only if it is a part of an established legitimization
offering robust protection, yes, now, you know firewall, combine multiple security function
into a single device, multiple security functions into a single device, including firewall,
intrusion presence and device and can enter fitting, this improper management and provide
complex protection, next generation firewall, integrate additional firewall capability with advanced
feature like application awareness, interest and privacy system, IPS and ideas are important,
interest and privacy system, interest and detection system and third intelligent, provide
provide deeper inspection, more recommended control over network traffic, however, IPS and
ideas were not axed in interview, they asked for a full-form bullet, but when you work,
when you have experience of one or two years, then if you're in doing for another company,
then they definitely ask, key tables and next step, this is the last PDF, so yeah, there's
a foundation knowledge, understand the roles of various network devices, so you have to
understand what end devices can do, what end devices are and what they do, OSM model integration,
how the OSM model work, so we will learn on that, don't take any pressure, don't take
any pressure, it's over a specific layer of the similar perform unique on-pressions, network
security basic, firewall are in-depth and for network protection and project type, bottoms
of security in the network infrastructure, I guess, all the things, do you have it all over?
Yes, so now we have to go into deep play off on network security, there's a holistic
goal test to a security advanced competition, in a wireless, when we have access point,
which is, so yeah, you have a router, you get a name when your router is on is called SSID
in a corporate, so you have to identify that, okay, so in SSID, you want a security, it's
VPA1, which is might of all VPA, VPA2, VPA3 or any other, so it's depend on the that, now
into press authentication 802.1, 1 AX, okay, it's for Wi-Fi 6, so this is how you have
to learn that which protocol is for use for what, and ROG AP detection, so ROG AP detection
likes malicious AP, which is in your network, so in your corporate, if someone is opening
their hotspot, it also requires a ROG AP address, because ROG AP detection, because it
find out that someone else is throwing it's SSID, it's a wireless connectivity in my area,
okay, maybe it can be harmful, so detect and tell us, so security, so in a switch is now
intelligence, so they come with more security, real-in segmentation, the SAP is swooping
API, the RPA inspection is panicking to protocol, so it's a lot of it, a reverse congregation,
we have to do in our network, and it's just a general terminology that we do, so yeah,
thank you very much, let's meet in our network section, bye bye for that, and just make
sure, no, keep it down, okay, keep it down in your notebook, a small, small points, not
everything, a small, small points, so that if you can read that point, whenever you
read that one, you can know, yeah, this is the proper definition of this system, okay, yeah,
so bye bye.